

DATA SCIENTIST

Details

+263 773 603 289 johnowhitaker@gmail.com

Links

Data Science Blog

Twitter

YouTube channel

Github

Online CV

Skills

Python

Data Wrangling

Deep Learning

Data Analytics & Visualization

GIS & Remote Sensing

JavaScript & WebGL

Hobbies

Birding, Rock Climbing, Creative Coding, Playing Music & Making DIY Instruments, Macro Photography, VR

Profile

Data scientist and educator based in Zimbabwe. Experienced applying machine learning to a wide variety of data and problem types. Creative and quick to learn new skills. Good at communicating with both technical and non-technical audiences. Passionate about finding ways to apply tools like deep learning and data science to make the world a better place.

Employment History

Data Science Consulting

JANUARY 2020 - FEBRUARY 2022

Contract work doing data science for various organizations, including:

- Zindi Preparing data for competitions, establishing performance baselines, writing tutorials and implementing the winning solutions.
- Ixio Analytics Working as a consultant on a number of projects.
- MyTrees and Bio-Innovation Zimbabwe Mapping forest loss in Zimbabwe and gathering base layers for future GIS analyses.

I took most of 2021 as a sabbatical, dialling back on my consulting in order to rest and pursue some additional interests including:

- Citizen science, recording some of Zimbabwe's incredible spider diversity
- Reigniting a passion for creative coding, which drove me to learn webGL and later steered me into the world of AI art.
- Teaching Deep Learning as a TA for Neuromatch Acadamy
- Pursuing a host of personal projects, some of which are documented on my blog (see 'Links' section)

Head Teacher (Data Science), iXperience

JUNE 2020 - AUGUST 2020

Taught a 6-week Data Science course with iXperience Remote 2020. Students learnt core Data Science skills and then put those into practice during a four-week internship. I was responsible for lectures and lecture prep, managing my three teaching assistants, overseeing the internship placement and helping the interns deliver on their projects.

Data Science Educator, African Leadership University

NOVEMBER 2017 - AUGUST 2020

Developed course content for the African Leadership University's Industrial Internet program as a consultant for Ixio Analytics, and then helped to deliver that content both online and in a series of in-person intensives. I helped create and run the Data Analytics, Machine Learning and Big Data modules, which ran for ~6 months of the year. We covered everything from basic analysis and visualization up to ML at scale with spark and hadoop.

Consultant (GIS, modelling and ecology)

DECEMBER 2013 - APRIL 2015

Worked with my mentor Clare Griffiths on a series of projects for Zimbabwean NGOs doing everything from fieldwork to GIS analysis and report writing.

Education

Bsc Hons. Electrical and Computer Engineering, University of Cape Town

FEBRUARY 2015 - NOVEMBER 2018